Finding Aid for Lorraine Beebe Papers ca. 1920-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lorraine Beebe Papers circa 1920-1981
Beebe, Lorraine B. (Lorraine Boekeloo)
Republican state senator, state coordinator of the Anderson for President campaign in 1980. Papers and photographs relating to her public career and to her interest in women's issues, especially abortion and the Equal Rights Amendment; also relating to her involvement with the President's Committee on Mental Retardation, her political activities and in the state senate; and scrapbook, 1966-1970, detailing political career.
8560 AC Aa 2 UAm
2.2 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Mrs. Beebe (donor no. 6829 ) donated her papers to the library in September 1982.
The collection is open for research.
Lorraine Beebe, neé Boekeloo, was born in Kalamazoo, Michigan. She graduated from Western Michigan University (BS 1932) and took graduate classes at Wayne State University (MS 1946) and the University of Michigan. After graduating from Western Michigan, Mrs. Beebe worked for the city of Kalamazoo for three years as an assistant city recreation director. In 1937 she moved to Dearborn, Michigan, and accepted the position of director of girl's and women's recreational activities. While working in Dearborn, Mrs. Beebe met her husband, Mr. Leo Beebe, who later became a Ford Motor Company executive. Mr. and Mrs. Beebe, who were divorced in the mid-1960's, had two children, Peter and Anne.
Mrs. Beebe was active in community affairs and education in the 1950's and 1960's. She was the first woman appointed to the Dearborn recreation commission; served as chairman and a member of the Advisory Board of the Dearborn chapter of the American Red Cross; guided the activities of the Youth Fellowship and Christian Education at the Christ Episcopal Church in Dearborn; taught and counseled students at Dearborn High School; and was a psychology instructor at Henry Ford Community College.
Mrs. Beebe has been interested and active in political causes for many years. She served as the chairman of Eisenhower's 1956 fund raising campaign in Dearborn and was a delegate to the 1964 Michigan Republican State Convention in Grand Rapids. Her first attempt to gain public office was an unsuccessful primary election for a Michigan state senate seat in 1964. She ran again for the state senate in 1966 and won both the Republican primary and the general election beating incumbent Democrat Edward J. Robinson. In the state senate, Mrs. Beebe was the first woman elected assistant majority leader. She chaired the Health, Social Services, and Retirement Committee, was vice chair of the Highways Committee, and was a member of the Labor Committee. She also served on numerous interim and special committees and commissions.
Senator Beebe, the only woman in the Michigan Senate, felt she represented both her senatorial district and the women of Michigan. The campaign to reform Michigan's abortion law became one of her primary concerns. In a speech before the Senate in 1969 during the abortion debate, Senator Beebe told the chamber of the therapeutic abortion she underwent years earlier. As a result of this speech, Senator Beebe gained national recognition and became a leading spokesperson for the pro-choice movement. Her pro-choice stance on the abortion issue was a major reason for her defeat in 1970.
Mrs. Beebe's commitment to political activity did not end with her Senate defeat. She was appointed to numerous Federal and State commissions and committees during the 1970's and was a much sought after consultant and lecturer on issues such as abortion, consumerism, women's issues, and political action. Mrs. Beebe was a member of the President's Committee on Mental Retardation (1970-1980); the Indian Affairs and National Inter-Agency Council (1972-1975); the Michigan Women's Council (1972-1978, chairwoman, 1972-1975); the Michigan Consumer Council (Executive Director, 1972-1974); the Michigan Criminal Justice Commission (1973-1976); the Advisory Council to the Michigan Indian Commission (chairperson, 1973-1975); the Michigan Society for Mental Health (Board Member, 1973-1975); the Michigan Health Council (1972-1976); and the Parole and Review Board, Michigan Office of Youth Services (Vice Chairperson).
Mrs. Beebe moved from Dearborn to Portage, Michigan, in 1977 where she continued working with various political movements. During the 1980 presidential campaign, she worked on behalf of the National Unity Campaign of John B. Anderson. She was nominated by Michigan National Unity Convention to run as Vice-President on Anderson's Michigan ticket. She withdrew her name when Anderson named former Wisconsin Governor Patrick Lucey as his vice presidential choice. During the 1980 campaign, Mrs. Beebe served as the Michigan State Coordinator for the Anderson ticket.
The collection concerns Beebe's public career and her interest in women's issues, especially abortion and the Equal Rights Amendment Also documented is her involvement with the President's Committee on Mental Retardation, her political activities and in the state senate. The papers of Lorraine Beebe have been arranged into biographical files; career files - private; career files - public; organizational files; speeches; correspondence; honors and awards/miscellaneous; and photographs.
Subjects:
Abortion--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Anderson, John Bayard, 1922-; Beebe, Lorraine B. (Lorraine Boekeloo); Elections--Michigan--1980.; Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; Legislators--Michigan.; Mentally handicapped--Michigan.; Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Presidents--United States--Election--1980.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; United States--Politics and government--1974-1977.; United States--Politics and government--1977-1981.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States. President's Committee on Mental Retardation.; Women legislators--Michigan.; Women's rights--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Beebe, Lorraine B. (Lorraine Boekeloo); Boekeloo family.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Kalamazoo (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Nixon, Pat, 1913-; Political elections--1980.; Politicians--Michigan.; Reagan, Ronald.; Republican Party (Mich.); Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Women--Political life.; Women's rights.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical Files
  The biographical series contain her resumes, newspaper articles about her, an oversize scrapbook, and materials concerning her family.
  - Vitas (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Articles circa 1920-1960 (Box 1)
  - Beebe Family (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1966-1970 (Volume AC)
- Career Files-Private Sector
  The private career files consist of papers generated by the Michigan headquarters of John B. Anderson's presidential campaign. There are also some files pertaining to Mrs. Beebe's one year position at Olivet College.
  - Michigan State Coordinator, Anderson for President 1980
    - Ballot Legal Problems, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Certificates of Nomination (Box 1)
    - City Precinct Targets (Box 1)
    - Convention (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - County Delegates and Caucuses, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Lucey's Filing for Vice-President (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Newspaper articles (Box 1)
    - Press releases (Box 1)
    - State Strategy memos (Box 1)
    - State Volunteers (Box 1)
    - State Convention proceedings, 9 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Washington Research Report (Michigan) (Box 1)
  - Olivet College 1975 (Box 1)
- Career Files-Public Sector
  The public career files are divided into two subseries, the federal government and the state government. The federal government subseries concerns Mrs. Beebe's activities with the President's Committee on Mental Retardation (1970-1980). The state government subseries concerns Mrs. Beebe's years in the Michigan Senate (1966-1970), the Women's Action Committee Against Crime (1968), the Michigan's Women's Commission (1972-1978), the State Planning Advisory Health Council (1973), the Michigan Consumer Council (1972-1974), the campaign for Michigan Secretary of State (1974), and the Governor's Task Force on Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions (1978).
  - Federal Government
    - President's Committee on Mental Retardation
      - 1970-1976 (Box 1)
      - 1977-1979 (Box 1)
      - Report "Curbing Abuse and Neglect in Our Mental Retardation Institutions" 1978 (Box 1)
  - State Government
    - State Senate 1966-1970
      - California Grape Boycott 1969 (Box 1)
      - Election Campaigns 1966, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Legislative Reports and Press Releases (Box 1)
      - Legislative Study Committee on Juvenile Delinquency (Box 1)
      - Michigan State Senate Committee on Abortion Reform (Box 2)
      - Newspaper Articles (Box 2)
      - Special Senate Committee to Investigate Colleges and Universities (Box 2)
    - Women's Action Committee Against Crime 1968 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Women's Commission 1972-1978 (Box 2)
    - State Planning Advisory Health Council 1973 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Consumer Council 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - Campaign for Michigan Secretary of State 1974 (Box 2)
    - Governor's Task Force on Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions 1978 (Box 2)
- Organizations
  The organization series reflects Mrs. Beebe's work in the Michigan ERA campaign (1972-1973) and the Michigan Abortion Rights Action League (1978-1979).
  - ERA-Michigan 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Abortion Rights Action League (MARAL) 1978-1979
    - Minutes and Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Michigan Medicaid Abortion Study: 1978 (Box 2)
- Speeches
  Mrs. Beebe's speeches (1966-1979) express her views on abortion rights, women's political awareness, WJR's My Point of View series, the 1974 Secretary of State campaign, as well as various other topics.
  - State Senator 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - WJR-My Point of View Series 1970-1974 (Box 2)
  - 1970-1974 and Undated (Box 2)
  - Secretary of State Campaign 1974 (Box 2)
  - 1975-1979 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The correspondence series (1940-1979) consists largely of letters resulting from Mrs. Beebe's senate speech revealing the fact of her abortion and letters received following her 1970 election defeat. The remaining correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - 1940-1965 (Box 2)
  - 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - 1970 (letters received after abortion announcement) (Box 2)
  - 1970 (After election defeat) (Box 2)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - 1973-1979 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous/Personal
  - Honors and Awards (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series includes photos relating to her public career and to her interest in women's issues, especially abortion. There are also family photos of the Boekeloo family of Kalamazoo, Michigan, and a photo of the Miller Ryder and Winterburn Company store in Kalamazoo.
  (See also oversize folder UAm)
  - Abortion rights activities 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Anderson Campaign 1980 (Box 3)
  - Awards (Box 3)
  - Campaigns (Box 3)
  - Colleagues (Box 3)
  - Constituents (Box 3)
  - Family (Box 3)
    (includes photo of Miller Ryder and Winterburn G., Kalamazoo, ca. 1915, See also oversize folder UAm)
  - Ford, Betty (Box 3)
  - Friends (early Kalamazoo) (Box 3)
  - Human Transplants Hearing 1969 (Box 3)
  - Livonia Women's Group (Box 3)
  - Meetings and speeches, unidentified (Box 3)
  - Milliken, William Grawn-signing legislation (Box 3)
  - Milliken, William Grawn (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Nixon, Richard and Pat (Box 3)
  - Portraits-early (Box 3)
  - Portraits-formal (Box 3)
  - Portraits-informal (Box 3)
  - Reagan, Ronald (Box 3)
  - Romney, George and Lenore (Box 3)
  - Senate Swearing in (Box 3)
  - Social Services (Box 3)
  - Youth Groups (Box 3)